Serge Grigoriev/Ballets Russes Archive
Music Division, Library of Congress
Guides to Special Collections in the Music Division of the Library of Congress
Serge Grigoriev/Ballets Russes Archive 1909-2009 (bulk 1909-1952)
ML31.G75
Grigoriev, S. L. (Sergeĭ Leonidovich), 1883-1968
1021 items 24 containers 18 linear feet
Music Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
The Serge Grigoriev/Ballets Russes Archive documents Grigoriev’s decades-long career as régisseur (rehearsal director) for both Diaghilev’s Ballets Russes and for Col. W. de Basil’s Ballets Russes de Monte Carlo. It consists primarily of photographs, photograph albums, and notes and manuscript drafts for Grigoriev’s book S.P. Diaghilev i ego ‘Russkii Balet’ 1909-1929, which was translated into English and published as The Diaghilev Ballet, 1909-1929. The archive also contains Grigoriev’s unpublished manuscript for his work Original’nyi Russkii Balet pod upravleniem Colonel W. De Basil 1932-1952. In addition, the archive includes choreographic notes, programs, additional writings by Grigoriev, clippings, tour information, and drawings.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Balanchine, George--Photographs.; Basil, W. de.; Basil, W. de.--Photographs.; Danilova, Alexandra, 1907-1997--Photographs.; Diaghilev, Serge, 1872-1929--Photographs.; Diaghilev, Serge, 1872-1929.; Doubrovska, Felia, 1896-1981--Photographs.; Grigorieva, Tamara--Photographs.; Grigorʹev, S. L. (Sergeĭ Leonidovich), 1883-1968--Photographs.; Grigorʹev, S. L. (Sergeĭ Leonidovich), 1883-1968.; Grigorʹev, S. L. (Sergeĭ Leonidovich), 1883-1968.; Grigorʹev, S. L. (Sergeĭ Leonidovich), 1883-1968. Diaghilev ballet, 1909-1929.; Jasinski, Roman, 1912-1991--Photographs.; Lichine, David--Photographs.; Lifar, Serge, 1905-1986--Photographs.; MacKenzie, Kenneth, d. 1999--Photographs.; Massine, Leonide, 1896-1979.; Morosova, Olga--Photographs.; Nemchinova, Vera--Photographs.; Nijinska, Bronislava, 1891-1972--Photographs.; Nijinsky, Waslaw, 1890-1950--Photographs.; Petroff, Paul--Photographs.; Riabouchinska, Tatiana--Photographs.; Rostov, Dmitri--Photographs.; Tchernicheva, Lubov--Photographs.; Toumanova, Tamara, 1917- --Photographs.; Verchinina, Nina--Photographs.
Organizations
Ballet Russe de Monte Carlo.; Ballets russes du Col. W. de Basil--Photographs.; Ballets russes du Col. W. de Basil.; Ballets russes--Photographs.; Ballets russes.; Ballets russes. Serge Grigoriev/Ballets Russes archive. 1909-2009.
Subjects
Ballet companies--Russia--Photographs.; Ballet companies--Russia.; Ballet dancers--Photographs.; Ballet dancers.; Ballet--Russia.; Ballet--Stage-setting and scenery.
Form/Genre
Photographic prints.; Programs.; Souvenir programs.
Administrative Information
Provenance
The material in the archive was purchased in 1999 and 2001. Related materials that detail both companies have been donated from a variety of sources or have been purchased.
Accruals
No further accruals are expected.
Related Material
The Library of Congress Music Division holds the special collections and archives of a number of significant figures from the Ballets Russes, including the
Adolph Bolm Collection
, the
Alexandra Danilova Collection
, the George Zoritch Archive of Photographs, the Bronislava Nijinska Collection, and the
Serge Diaghilev/Serge Lifar Collection
.
Access and Restrictions
The Serge Grigoriev/Ballets Russes Archive is open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Music Division prior to visiting in order to determine whether the desired materials will be available at that time.
Certain restrictions to use or copying of materials may apply.
Biographical Note
The Ballets Russes de Serge Diaghilev (also known as Diaghilev’s Ballets Russes) was a creation of the great Russian impresario, Serge Diaghilev. In 1907 Diaghilev presented a festival of Russian music at the Paris Opera and, in 1908, he returned to offer six performances of Mussorgsky’s opera Boris Godunov, which marked the first performance of the opera outside Russia. Upon his re-engagement in 1909, Diaghilev added four ballets to his operatic presentations. The enormous popularity of the ballets was such that in 1910 Diaghilev offered only “Ballets Russes.” Because many of the Russian dancers performing with Diaghilev were members of the Maryinsky Ballet in Saint Petersburg, they were allowed to travel only when their season was over and Diaghilev soon realized the importance of creating a permanent dance company in the West.
From 1909 to 1912, the Russian choreographer Michel Fokine’s works dominated the repertory of Diaghilev’s Ballets Russes, but Fokine’s resignation allowed Diaghilev to re-conceptualize the company and to commission works that fulfilled his personal aesthetic. Vaslav Nijinsky was anointed as the choreographer who would open the door to Diaghilev’s principles of modernism in ballet. Thereafter, the succession of choreographers that continued Diaghilev’s ideals included Léonide Massine, Bronislava Nijinska, and George Balanchine.
Between 1918 and 1922, Diaghilev’s Ballets Russes performed for long periods of time in London; however, by the mid-1920s, the company split its time between Paris and Monte Carlo. In Monte Carlo, Diaghilev enjoyed the support of the ruling Grimaldi family and was also providing dancers and choreographers for most of the Théâtre de Monte-Carlo’s operatic productions.
One of Diaghilev’s most significant legacies was his collaboration with other artists. For example, he commissioned scores from Debussy, Ravel, Richard Strauss, Satie, Poulenc, and Prokofiev, and is credited with establishing Stravinsky’s international career. Diaghilev also worked closely with the numerous painters and sculptors who created designs for his company, including Bakst, Benois, Matisse, Picasso, Rouault, Gris, Braque, Utrillo, and Miró. However, perhaps his greatest contribution to the world of ballet was his support of the choreographers Nijinsky, Massine, Nijinska, and Balanchine. Likewise, he launched the careers of many dancers, including names such as Adolph Bolm, Léonide Massine, Lydia Lopokova, Olga Spessivtseva, Anton Dolin, Alexandra Danilova, Alicia Markova, and Serge Lifar.
Throughout its existence, Diaghilev’s Ballets Russes set new standards for ballet technique and played an important role in creating a significant body of choreographic works—many of which continue to be performed in the repertories of ballet companies throughout the world.
After Serge Diaghilev’s death in 1929, René Blum was appointed director of ballet at the Théâtre de Monte-Carlo. Blum was determined to establish a new Russian ballet company at the Théâtre and, in 1931 he met Colonel Wassily de Basil. De Basil had emigrated to Paris in 1919 and was the director of L’Opéra Russe à Paris. In late 1931, de Basil and Blum created Les Ballets Russes de Monte Carlo with George Balanchine as ballet master and Boris Kochno as artistic director. The company’s first season opened at the Théâtre de Monte-Carlo in 1932 and, at the end of the year, Balanchine left and was replaced by Léonide Massine. Massine remained with the company until 1937. After a disagreement with Blum in 1934, de Basil became the sole director and the company became known as the Ballets Russes de Colonel W. de Basil (later called the Original Ballet Russe).
When de Basil died in 1951, his associate George Kirsta organized a new company that opened four months later at the Wimbledon Theatre, England. Despite some local touring, the company performed for the last time in January 1952. Known variously throughout the years as the Ballets Russes de Colonel W. de Basil (1932-1938), Colonel W. de Basil’s Ballet Russe (1937, in New York), Educational Ballets Limited (1938), Covent Garden Russian Ballet (1938-1940), and the Original Ballet Russe (1940-1952), the company crisscrossed the globe and was instrumental in the popularization of ballet worldwide.
Serge Grigoriev studied ballet at the Imperial Theatre School in Saint Petersburg and, in 1909, Diaghilev appointed him as company régisseur (rehearsal director) for the first Paris season of his Ballets Russes. Grigoriev remained in this position until Diaghliev’s death in 1929. Upon the formation of the Ballets Russes de Monte Carlo, Grigoriev served once again as régisseur, remaining with the company until its dissolution in 1952. During the 1950s, along with his wife, dancer Lubov Tchernicheva, he staged revivals of Fokine ballets for Sadler’s Wells Ballet (later known as the Royal Ballet), the London Festival Ballet, and La Scala, and oversaw rehearsals for Massine ballets. Grigoriev died on 28 June 1968.
Date Event
1883 Serge Grigoriev (Sergei Leonidovich Grigor’ev) is born 5 October in Tichvin, Russia.
1900 Grigoriev enters the Maryinsky corps de ballet, where he remains until 1912.
1909 Grigoriev is appointed Serge Diaghilev’s company régisseur (rehearsal director) for the first Paris season of the Ballets Russes de Serge Diaghilev (also known as Diaghilev’s Ballets Russes). Grigoriev marries dancer Lubov Tchernicheva. Diaghilev’s Ballets Russes premieres works by choreographer Michel Fokine, including Le Pavillon d’Armide (music by Tcherepnine) and Les Sylphides (music by Chopin).
1910 Grigoriev plays the character role of the Shah Shariar in Michel Fokine’s Schéhérazade (music by Rimsky-Korsakov) for Diaghilev’s Ballets Russes, Paris. Diaghilev’s Ballets Russes premieres Fokine’s L’Oiseau de Feu [The Firebird] (music by Stravinsky). This is the first score by Stravinsky to be commissioned especially for a ballet.
1911 Diaghilev’s Ballets Russes premieres Fokine’s Petrouchka. The company makes its first visit to London.
1912 After Diaghilev promotes Vaslav Nijinsky as a choreographer, Michel Fokine leaves the Ballets Russes. Diaghilev’s Ballets Russes premieres Nijinsky’s L’Après-midi d’un Faune (music by Faure) and Jeux (music by Debussy).
1913 Diaghilev’s Ballets Russes premieres Nijinsky’s Le Sacre du Printemps [The Rite of Spring] (music by Stravinsky). After Vaslav Nijinsky marries Romola de Pulszky, Diaghilev fires Vaslav Nijinsky from the Ballets Russes.
1914 Grigoriev plays the character role of Guidone in Fokine’s Le coq d’or (music by Rimsky-Korsakov) for Diaghilev’s Ballets Russes. Léonide Massine makes his debut with Diaghilev’s Ballets Russes in the title role of Fokine’s Die Josephslegende. In support of her brother Nijinsky, dancer Bronislava Nijinska leaves the Ballets Russes. The company makes its first tour of South America.
1915 Le Soleil de Nuit (music by Rimsky-Korsakov) is premiered with Massine acting as both choreographer and principal dancer.
1916 Ballets Russes makes their first tour of the United States, returning again for a second tour, 1916-1917.
1917 Diaghilev’s Ballets Russes premieres Massine’s Parade (music by Satie).
1919 Grigoriev plays the character role of the Russian Merchant in Léonide Massine’s La Boutique fantasque (music by Rossini, orchestrated by Respighi) for Diaghilev’s Ballets Russes, London.
1921 Diaghilev dismisses Massine from the company. Diaghilev’s Ballets Russes produces a version of Marius Petipa’s 1890's The Sleeping Beauty. Retitled The Sleeping Princess, it is the first full production of a complete Petipa ballet to be performed outside Russia. Bronislava Nijinska returns to Diaghilev’s Ballets Russes for four years.
1922 Diaghilev presents a divertissement created from Petipa’s The Sleeping Beauty (music by Tchaikovsky). The resulting work is called Aurora’s Wedding with staging and some new choreography by Bronislava Nijinska. Diaghilev’s Ballets Russes premieres Bronislava Nijinska’s Le Renard (music by Stravinsky).
1923 Diaghilev’s Ballets Russes premieres Nijinska’s Les Noces (music by Stravinsky).
1924 Diaghilev’s Ballets Russes premieres Nijinska’s Les Biches (music by Poulenc); Les Fâcheux (music by Auric); Night on Bald Mountain (ballet from the opera Sorochintsy Fair, music by Mussorgsky); and Le Train Bleu (music by Milhaud). Diaghilev engages George Balanchine as ballet master. During his tenure with the company (1924-1929), he creates ten ballets.
1928 Diaghilev’s Ballets Russes premieres George Balanchine’s Apollon musagète (music by Stravinsky).
1929 Diaghilev’s Ballets Russes premieres George Balanchine’s Le Fils prodigue [Prodigal Son] (music by Prokofiev). Serge Diaghilev dies on 19 August.
1932 Grigoriev joins Colonel Wassily de Basil’s Ballets Russes de Monte Carlo as company régisseur.
1933 The company makes its London debut at the Alhambra Theatre on 4 July. Sol Hurok presents the company in New York at the St. James Theatre on 22 December.
1934 The company begins a North American Tour in October in Mexico City. The company also performs in Canada and California.
1935 The company performs at the Metropolitan Opera House in New York.
1936 Invited to Austrialia, de Basil forms a second company for a tour that lasts until July 1937.
1937 Massine’s contract is extended to cover part of the fall and winter American tour.
1938 Massine gives his last performance at the San Francisco Opera House on 30 January. Massine becomes artistic director of a new company, the Ballet Russe de Monte Carlo, with Sergei J. Denham as general director. Colonel W. de Basil’s Ballets Russes performs at Covent Garden, London, under the name Educational Ballets Limited.
1939 Under the name Covent Garden Russian Ballet, the company tours Australia and New Zealand from September to April 1939. Touring under the name Original Ballet Russe, the company returns to the United States in October.
1941 The Original Ballet Russe arrives in Cuba. The dancers receive a cut in salary and seventeen of them stage a strike. The company eventually makes its way back to the United States.
1942 The company tours Brazil, Uruguay, and Argentina. By 1943 the company is in residence at the Teatro Colón, Buenos Aires. In addition, the company tours other South American countries. The Original Ballet Russe remains in South America until 1946.
1947 The Original Ballet Russe returns to New York for a season at the Metropolitan Opera House, tours coast-to-coast and, presents a second New York Season. The company returns to Europe and prepares for a season at Covent Garden, which takes place July-September. David Lichine’s Graduation Ball is seen in London for the first time.
1948 After seasons in Paris and Brussels, de Basil takes the company on a tour of Spain and North Africa that lasts seven months. The company is disbanded on 6 November.
1951 Colonel Wassily de Basil dies on 27 July.
1952 De Basil’s associate, George Kirsta, resurrects a new Original Ballet Russe, which offers its last performance at London’s Adelphi Theatre on 26 January. Serge Grigoriev retires.
1953 Grigoriev publishes The Diaghilev Ballet 1909-1929.
1954-1955 Grigoriev and his wife stage Fokine’s The Firebird and Les Sylphides for Britain’s Royal Ballet.
1956 Grigoriev serves one year as régisseur for London’s Royal Ballet.
1957 Grigoriev and his wife, Lubov Tcherinova, stage Petrouchka for the Royal Ballet.
1968 Serge Grigoriev dies in London on 28 June.
Scope and Content Note
The Serge Grigoriev/Ballets Russes Archive is comprised of materials that document Serge Grigoriev’s career as a dancer and as régisseur (rehearsal director) for the Ballets Russes de Serge Diaghilev (1909-1929). Grigoriev served in the same capacity for the Ballets Russes de Colonel W. de Basil (1932-1952). The manuscripts, photographs, and other documents that are included in this Archive provide one of the richest collections of information on these two dance companies available anywhere.
Although the majority of the materials in the Serge Grigoriev/Ballets Russes Archive relate to the companies of Diaghilev and de Basil, the Archive contains several items from another Russian ballet company, the Ballet Russe de Monte Carlo. By 1937 differences between Massine and de Basil led to the formation of a company for Massine with backers that included Sergei J. Denham, who eventually became the general director. The Ballet Russe de Monte Carlo existed from 1938 to 1962.
Organization of the Serge Grigoriev/Ballets Russes Archive
The Serge Grigoriev/Ballets Russes Archive is organized into six series:
Writings by Serge Grigoriev
Photographs
Photograph Albums
Programs
Writings about the Ballets Russes de Serge Diaghilev and the Ballet Russe de Monte Carlo
Ballets Russes: Company members; Clippings; Tour Information; Drawings
http://lccn.loc.gov/2010561019
Container List
- Writings by Serge Grigoriev (Boxes 1-6)
  The core of the Serge Grigoriev/Ballets Russes Archive is the collection of manuscript drafts for his work The Diaghilev Ballet 1909-1929 (translated into English by Vera Bowen and published in 1953) and an unpublished manuscript titled Original’nyi Russkii Balet 1932-1952 (also called Original’nyi Russkii Balet pod upravleniem Colonel W. De Basil 1932-1952 [The Original Ballet Russe under the management of Colonel W. De Basil 1932-1952]). Other notebooks contain descriptions and cast lists for choreographic works performed by the Ballets Russes de Serge Diaghilev (also known as Diaghilev’s Ballets Russes) and Ballets Russes de Monte Carlo (also known as the Original Ballet Russe).
  - Manuscript draft of S.P. Diaghilev i ego ‘Russkii Balet’ 1909-1929 [The Diaghilev Ballet 1909-1929] (Box 1)
  - Five notebooks, in Russian, occasional corrections in pencil; dated London, 24 April 1952
  - Two notebooks, containing details of the choreographies for many ballets for both the Ballets Russes de Serge Diaghilev and the Ballets Russes de Col. W. De Basil, c.1926-1936 (Box 2)
  - Manuscript draft of Original’nyi Russkii Balet pod upravleniem Colonel W. De Basil 1932-1952 [The Original Ballet Russe under the management of Colonel W. De Basil 1932-1952], In Russian, numerous corrections; dated 2 September 1952 to 18 August 1960. This unpublished draft includes notes and/or cast lists for works that include: Les Sylphides, Petrouchka, L’Amour Sorcier, Swan Lake, La Concurrence, Cotillon, Le Bourgeois Gentilhomme, Le Beau Danube, Beach, École de Dance, Scuola di Ballo, Nocturne, Carnaval, Tricorne, Les Présages, The Firebird, Boutique Fantasque, Union Pacific, Choreartium, Aurora’s Wedding, Les Imaginaires, Schéhérazade, Femmes de Bonne Humeur [Good Humored Ladies], Thamar, Contes Russes, Le Bal, Jardin Public, Les Cent Baisers, Danses Slaves et Tziganes, Papillon, La Pavillon d’Armide, Cleopatra (Box 3)
  - Manuscript copy of Original’nyi Russkii Balet 1932-1952, in Russian, with a 35-page typed appendix in English of ballets performed by the company during those dates (Box 4)
  - Collection of loose working notes relating to Grigoriev’s manuscripts, comprising: (Box 5)
    - • An early manuscript draft from Russkovo Baleta S.P. Diaghileva, in Russian, covering 1948; dated 15 November 1949
    - • Manuscript in Russian, titled Kratkaia Biographia S.P. Diaghilev i ego deyatelnosti 1872-1929 [A Short biography of Diaghilev and his Works]
    - • Manuscript and typed lists of dancers, artists, composers, and others involved in the company’s productions; manuscript lists of Diaghilev’s productions; a manuscript account of Diaghilev’s relations with his artistic collaborators, including Derain, Larionov, Picasso, and Matisse
    - • Various other working notes, including choreographic diagrams, manuscript and typed notes relating to the Ballets Russes
  - Manuscript draft of Original’nyi Russkii Balet [The Original Ballet Russe 1932-1952], five notebooks in Russian; dated 2 September 1952 and 18 August 1960 (Box 6)
- Photographs (Boxes 9; 14; 17-18; 20; 23-24)
  This series contains photographs of most of the principal artists associated with Diaghilev’s Ballets Russes and the Ballets Russes de Monte Carlo.
  - Personal Names (Box 9; 14; 17-18; 20; 23-24)
    - Algeranoff, Harcourt (Box-folder 24/3)
    - Alonso, Alberto (Box-folder 24/3)
    - Alonso, Alberto and Denisova, Alexandra (Box 17)
    - Amsermet, Ernest; Tchernicheva, Lubov; Lifar, Serge; Nikitina, Alice; and Doubrovska, Felia (Box 9)
    - Balanchine, George; Tchernicheva, Lubov; and Doubrovska, Felia (Box 9)
    - Balanchine, George; Tchernicheva, Lubov; Doubrovska, Felia; and Lifar, Serge (Box 9)
    - Baronova, Irina (Box-folder 23/1; 24/3; 24/5)
    - Baronova, Irina and Petroff, Paul (Box-folder 23/2)
    - Baronova, Irina and Lichine, David (Box 14)
    - Borovansky, Edouard; Rostov, Dmitri; and Tchernicheva, Lubov (Box 18)
    - Bousloff, Serge and Grigorieva, Tamara (Box 14)
    - Conus, Natalie (Box-folder 23/3; 9)
    - Danilova, Alexandra (Box-folder 23/4; 14)
    - Danilova, Alexandra and Petroff, Paul (Box 14)
    - Danilova, Alexandra; Tchernicheva, Lubov; Grigoriev, Serge; and Doubrovska, Felia (Box 9)
    - de Basil, Col. W. (Box-folder 23/5; 14; 17; 20)
    - de Basil, Col. W. (with others) (Box-folder 23/6; 14; 20)
    - Denisova, Alexandra (Patricia Denise Meyers; also known as Patricia Meyers and as Patricia Denise) (Box 17)
    - Denisova, Alexandra and Osato, Sono (Box 17)
    - Diaghilev, Serge and Kochno, Boris (Box 9)
    - Diaghilev, Serge; Kochno, Boris; and Picasso’s children (Box 9)
    - Dokoudovsky, Vladimir (Box-folder 24/1; 24/5)
    - Doroudovsky, M. (Box-folder 24/6)
    - Doubrovska, Felia; George Balanchine; and Tchernicheva, Lubov (Box 9)
    - Doubrovska, Felia; Tchernicheva, Lubov; Grigoriev, Serge; and Danilova, Alexandra (Box 9)
    - Doubrovska, Felia; Tcherkas, Constantin; and Tchernicheva, Lubov (Box 9)
    - Federov, Michel and Tchernicheva, Lubov (Box 9)
    - Geltser, Ekaterina (Box-folder 23/7)
    - Gilpin, John (?) and Riabouchinska, Tatiana (Box-folder 23/23)
    - Grigoriev, Serge (Box-folder 23/8; 17; 20)
    - Grigoriev, Serge and Tchernicheva, Lubov (Box 17; 9)
    - Grigoriev, Serge (with others) (Box-folder 23/9; 20)
    - Grigoriev, Serge with de Basil, Col W. (Box-folder 23/10)
    - Grigoriev, Serge; Tchernicheva, Lubov; Danilova, Alexandra; and Doubrovska, Felia (Box 9)
    - Grigorieva, Tamara (Box-folder 23/11; 14; 17)
    - Grigorieva, Tamara and Bousloff, Serge (Box 14)
    - Grigorieva, Tamara and Lichine, David (Box 14)
    - Grigorieva, Tamara; Lichine, David; Toumanova, Tamar; and Riabouchinska, Tatiana (Box 14)
    - Grigorieva, Tamara and Massine, Léonide (Box 14)
    - Grigorieva, Tamara and Morosova, Olga (Box 14)
    - Grigorieva, Tamara; Nelidova, Vera; and Tchinarova, Tamara (Box 14)
    - Grigorieva, Tamara and Petroff, Paul (Box 14)
    - Grigorieva, Tamara and Stogonova, Nina (Box 14)
    - Greigorieva, Tamara and other(s) (Box-folder 24/3; 17)
    - Hyman, Prudence (also known as Strogova, Pauline) (Box 14)
    - Jasinski, Roman (Box-folder 24/5; 24/6; 17)
    - Jasinski, Roman and Tchernicheva, Lubov (Box 18)
    - Jasinski, Roman; Tchernicheva, Lubov; and Mackenzie, Kenneth (Box 18)
    - Karsavina, Tamara (Box-folder 23/12; 20)
    - Karlewska, Jadwiga (Box-folder 23/13)
    - Kochno, Boris and Diaghilev, Serge (Box 9)
    - Kochno, Boris; Diaghilev, Serge; and Picasso’s children (Box 9)
    - Kshessinska, Matilda (Box-folder 23/14; 14)
    - Kyasht, Lydia (Box-folder 23/15)
    - Lazowski, Yurek (Box-folder 24/3; 17)
    - Lazowski, Yurek with others (Box 17)
    - Leskova, Tatiana (Box-folder 23/16; 24/6)
    - Lichine, David (Box 17; 18)
    - Lichine, David and Baronova, Irina (Box 14)
    - Lichine, David and Grigorieva, Tamara (Box 14)
    - Lichine, David; Grigorieva, Tamara; Toumanova, Tamar; and Riabouchinska, Tatiana (Box 14)
    - Lichine, David and Riabouchinska, Tatiana (Box-folder 24/6)
    - Lichine, David and others (Box 18)
    - Lifar, Serge (Box 17; 20)